<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-13T09:18:53-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Asymptotic Safety Seminars</title><subtitle>Asymptotic Safety Seminars. An international online seminar series. Since 2011.&gt;-</subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Ivano Basile: Asymptotic safety and the swampland</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/future/2022/05/30/Ivano-Basile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ivano Basile: Asymptotic safety and the swampland" /><published>2022-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/future/2022/05/30/Ivano-Basile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/future/2022/05/30/Ivano-Basile.html">&lt;p&gt;We propose testing the paradigm of asymptotically safe gravity using swampland conjectures. As a first step in this direction, we explore the infrared regime of asymptotically safe gravity in a toy model, quadratic gravity at one loop. We identify the hypersurface spanned by the endpoints of asymptotically safe renormalization group trajectories. These comprise the allowed values of higher-derivative couplings as well as standard logarithmic form factors. We determine the intersection of this hypersurface with the regions of parameter space allowed by the de Sitter conjecture, the trans-Planckian censorship conjecture and the weak gravity conjecture under the hypothesis of electromagnetic duality. The latter two depend on some order-one constants, for generic values of which we show that the overlap region is a proper subspace of the asymptotically safe hypersurface. Moreover, the latter lies inside the region allowed by the weak gravity conjecture. To conclude, we outline various extensions of this program, focusing on sharper bounds derived in the swampland and bootstrap literatures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><category term="future" /><summary type="html">We propose testing the paradigm of asymptotically safe gravity using swampland conjectures. As a first step in this direction, we explore the infrared regime of asymptotically safe gravity in a toy model, quadratic gravity at one loop. We identify the hypersurface spanned by the endpoints of asymptotically safe renormalization group trajectories. These comprise the allowed values of higher-derivative couplings as well as standard logarithmic form factors. We determine the intersection of this hypersurface with the regions of parameter space allowed by the de Sitter conjecture, the trans-Planckian censorship conjecture and the weak gravity conjecture under the hypothesis of electromagnetic duality. The latter two depend on some order-one constants, for generic values of which we show that the overlap region is a proper subspace of the asymptotically safe hypersurface. Moreover, the latter lies inside the region allowed by the weak gravity conjecture. To conclude, we outline various extensions of this program, focusing on sharper bounds derived in the swampland and bootstrap literatures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maximilian Becker: Background Independent Field Quantization with Sequences of Gravity-Coupled Approximants</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/09/Maximilian-Becker.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maximilian Becker: Background Independent Field Quantization with Sequences of Gravity-Coupled Approximants" /><published>2022-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/09/Maximilian-Becker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/09/Maximilian-Becker.html">&lt;p&gt;We apply the new quantization scheme outlined in M. Becker and M. Reuter, Phys. Rev. D 102, 125001 (2020), to explore the influence which quantum vacuum fluctuations of the spacetime metric exert on the universes of quantum Einstein gravity, which is regarded an effective theory here. The scheme promotes the principle of background independence to the level of the regularized precursors of a quantum field theory (“approximants”) and severely constrains admissible regularization schemes. Without any tuning of parameters, we find that the zero point oscillations of linear gravitons on maximally symmetric spacetimes do not create the commonly expected cosmological constant problem of a cutoff-size curvature. On the contrary, metric fluctuations are found to reduce positive curvatures to arbitrarily tiny and ultimately vanishing values when the cutoff is lifted. This suggests that flat space could be the distinguished ground state of pure quantum gravity. Our results contradict traditional beliefs founded upon background- dependent calculations whose validity must be called into question therefore.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We apply the new quantization scheme outlined in M. Becker and M. Reuter, Phys. Rev. D 102, 125001 (2020), to explore the influence which quantum vacuum fluctuations of the spacetime metric exert on the universes of quantum Einstein gravity, which is regarded an effective theory here. The scheme promotes the principle of background independence to the level of the regularized precursors of a quantum field theory (“approximants”) and severely constrains admissible regularization schemes. Without any tuning of parameters, we find that the zero point oscillations of linear gravitons on maximally symmetric spacetimes do not create the commonly expected cosmological constant problem of a cutoff-size curvature. On the contrary, metric fluctuations are found to reduce positive curvatures to arbitrarily tiny and ultimately vanishing values when the cutoff is lifted. This suggests that flat space could be the distinguished ground state of pure quantum gravity. Our results contradict traditional beliefs founded upon background- dependent calculations whose validity must be called into question therefore.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Edoardo D’Angelo: Wetterich equation on lorentzian manifolds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/02/Edoardo-D'Angelo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Edoardo D’Angelo: Wetterich equation on lorentzian manifolds" /><published>2022-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/02/Edoardo-D'Angelo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/02/Edoardo-D'Angelo.html">&lt;p&gt;The Wetterich equation governs the renormalization flow of the effective action under the scaling of an IR cutoff. In this talk, I introduce a generalization of the Wetterich approach to scalar field theories in generic, Hadamard states on globally hyperbolic, Lorentzian spacetimes, using techniques developed in the perturbative Algebraic Quantum Field Theory framework. The main novel ingredient is the use of a local regulator, which preserves the local covariance and unitarity of the theory while regularizing the infrared divergences. As a proof of concept, I also briefly discuss the application of the theory to thermal states in Minkowski and to the Bunch-Davies vacuum in de Sitter space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">The Wetterich equation governs the renormalization flow of the effective action under the scaling of an IR cutoff. In this talk, I introduce a generalization of the Wetterich approach to scalar field theories in generic, Hadamard states on globally hyperbolic, Lorentzian spacetimes, using techniques developed in the perturbative Algebraic Quantum Field Theory framework. The main novel ingredient is the use of a local regulator, which preserves the local covariance and unitarity of the theory while regularizing the infrared divergences. As a proof of concept, I also briefly discuss the application of the theory to thermal states in Minkowski and to the Bunch-Davies vacuum in de Sitter space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gustavo de Brito: Nonvanishing gravitational contribution to matter beta functions for vanishing dimensionful regulators</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/25/Gustavo-de-Brito.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gustavo de Brito: Nonvanishing gravitational contribution to matter beta functions for vanishing dimensionful regulators" /><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/25/Gustavo-de-Brito</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/25/Gustavo-de-Brito.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will explore the effect of quantum gravity on matter couplings within a Renormalization Group framework. In particular, I will focus on results obtained from a class of interpolating regulators that allow us to extract certain universal pieces from non-universal quantities. I will discuss an explicit example of how misleading conclusions can be drawn by analyzing the gravitational contributions to beta functions instead of analyzing universal quantities, such as critical exponents, that can be extracted from the beta functions. This could be key to explaining the differences between perturbative studies and Functional Renormalization Group studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk, I will explore the effect of quantum gravity on matter couplings within a Renormalization Group framework. In particular, I will focus on results obtained from a class of interpolating regulators that allow us to extract certain universal pieces from non-universal quantities. I will discuss an explicit example of how misleading conclusions can be drawn by analyzing the gravitational contributions to beta functions instead of analyzing universal quantities, such as critical exponents, that can be extracted from the beta functions. This could be key to explaining the differences between perturbative studies and Functional Renormalization Group studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christof Wetterich: The quantum gravity connection between inflation and quintessence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/11/Christof-Wetterich.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christof Wetterich: The quantum gravity connection between inflation and quintessence" /><published>2022-04-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/11/Christof-Wetterich</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/11/Christof-Wetterich.html">&lt;p&gt;The scaling solution of the functional flow in dilaton quantum gravity leads to highly predictive cosmology. Inflation and quintessence can both be described by a single scalar field. The cosmic time evolution of this cosmon field realizes a crossover from the region of an ultraviolet fixed point in the infinite past to an infrared fixed point in the infinite future. This amounts to a transition from early inflation to late dynamical dark energy, with intermediate radiation and matter domination. The scaling solution of the renormalization flow in quantum gravity connects the two fixed points. It provides for the essential characteristics of the scalar potential needed for the crossover cosmology and solves the cosmological constant problem dynamically. The quantum scale symmetry at the infrared fixed point protects the tiny mass of the cosmon and suppresses the cosmon coupling to atoms without the need of a non-linear screening mechanism, thereby explaining apparent issues of fine tuning. For a given  content of particles the scaling solution of quantum gravity is a predictive framework for the properties of inflation and dynamical dark energy. No flow away from the scaling solution may be needed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">The scaling solution of the functional flow in dilaton quantum gravity leads to highly predictive cosmology. Inflation and quintessence can both be described by a single scalar field. The cosmic time evolution of this cosmon field realizes a crossover from the region of an ultraviolet fixed point in the infinite past to an infrared fixed point in the infinite future. This amounts to a transition from early inflation to late dynamical dark energy, with intermediate radiation and matter domination. The scaling solution of the renormalization flow in quantum gravity connects the two fixed points. It provides for the essential characteristics of the scalar potential needed for the crossover cosmology and solves the cosmological constant problem dynamically. The quantum scale symmetry at the infrared fixed point protects the tiny mass of the cosmon and suppresses the cosmon coupling to atoms without the need of a non-linear screening mechanism, thereby explaining apparent issues of fine tuning. For a given content of particles the scaling solution of quantum gravity is a predictive framework for the properties of inflation and dynamical dark energy. No flow away from the scaling solution may be needed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rudrajit Banerjee: The spatial Functional Renormalization Group and Hadamard states on cosmological spacetimes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/28/Rudrajit-Banerjee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rudrajit Banerjee: The spatial Functional Renormalization Group and Hadamard states on cosmological spacetimes" /><published>2022-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/28/Rudrajit-Banerjee</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/28/Rudrajit-Banerjee.html">&lt;p&gt;A spatial variant of the Functional Renormalization Group (FRG) is introduced on (Lorentzian signature) globally hyperbolic spacetimes. Through its perturbative expansion it is argued that such a FRG must inevitably be state dependent and that it should be based on a Hadamard state. A concrete implementation is presented for scalar quantum fields on flat Friedmann-Lemaître spacetimes. The universal ultraviolet behavior of Hadamard states allows the flow to be matched to the one-loop renormalized flow (where strict removal of the ultraviolet cutoff requires a tower of potentials, one for each power of the Ricci scalar). The state-dependent infrared behavior of the flow is investigated for States of Low Energy, which are Hadamard states deemed to be viable vacua for a pre-inflationary period. A simple time-dependent infrared fixed point equation (resembling that in Minkowski space) arises for any scale factor, with analytically computable corrections coding the non-perturbative ramifications of the Hadamard property in the infrared.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">A spatial variant of the Functional Renormalization Group (FRG) is introduced on (Lorentzian signature) globally hyperbolic spacetimes. Through its perturbative expansion it is argued that such a FRG must inevitably be state dependent and that it should be based on a Hadamard state. A concrete implementation is presented for scalar quantum fields on flat Friedmann-Lemaître spacetimes. The universal ultraviolet behavior of Hadamard states allows the flow to be matched to the one-loop renormalized flow (where strict removal of the ultraviolet cutoff requires a tower of potentials, one for each power of the Ricci scalar). The state-dependent infrared behavior of the flow is investigated for States of Low Energy, which are Hadamard states deemed to be viable vacua for a pre-inflationary period. A simple time-dependent infrared fixed point equation (resembling that in Minkowski space) arises for any scale factor, with analytically computable corrections coding the non-perturbative ramifications of the Hadamard property in the infrared.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chris Ripken: De Sitter scattering amplitudes in the Born approximation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/21/Chris-Ripken.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chris Ripken: De Sitter scattering amplitudes in the Born approximation" /><published>2022-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/21/Chris-Ripken</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/21/Chris-Ripken.html">&lt;p&gt;A basic calculation in QFT is the construction of the Yukawa potential from a tree-level scattering amplitude. In the massless limit, this reproduces the 1/r potential. For gravity, scattering mediated by a massless graviton is thus consistent with the Newtonian potential.
In de Sitter spacetime, the cosmological constant gives rise to a mass-like term in the graviton propagator. This raises the question what the classical potential looks like when taking into account curvature effects.
In this talk, I will introduce an operator-based formalism to compute scattering amplitudes in curved spacetime, and I will show how to construct the Newtonian potential in a dS background. Remarkably, the potential gives rise to an additional repulsive force, and encodes the de Sitter horizon in a novel and non-trivial way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">A basic calculation in QFT is the construction of the Yukawa potential from a tree-level scattering amplitude. In the massless limit, this reproduces the 1/r potential. For gravity, scattering mediated by a massless graviton is thus consistent with the Newtonian potential. In de Sitter spacetime, the cosmological constant gives rise to a mass-like term in the graviton propagator. This raises the question what the classical potential looks like when taking into account curvature effects. In this talk, I will introduce an operator-based formalism to compute scattering amplitudes in curved spacetime, and I will show how to construct the Newtonian potential in a dS background. Remarkably, the potential gives rise to an additional repulsive force, and encodes the de Sitter horizon in a novel and non-trivial way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renata Ferrero: Relational Observables in Asymptotically Safe Gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/14/Renata-Ferrero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renata Ferrero: Relational Observables in Asymptotically Safe Gravity" /><published>2022-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/14/Renata-Ferrero</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/14/Renata-Ferrero.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest issues for a quantum theory of gravitation is how to generalise the notion of local observable quantities. A viable approach is to construct a physical local reference frame and give physical meaning to the components of any tensor evaluated in this frame: all measurements of tensor or scalar fields can be thought of as relational observables.
The lack of observables is a major critique of the current Asymptotic Safety program. However, in the last years, within the functional renormalisation group framework an equation to evaluate the flow and the scaling dimension of composite operators has been developed. Relational observables are therefore natural candidates for composite operators.
We introduce an approach to compute the renormalisation group flow of relational observables in quantum gravity which evolve from their microscopic expressions towards the full quantum expectation value. These methods can be applied to a large class of relational observables within a derivative expansion for different physical coordinate systems. Based on arXiv:2112.02118.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">One of the greatest issues for a quantum theory of gravitation is how to generalise the notion of local observable quantities. A viable approach is to construct a physical local reference frame and give physical meaning to the components of any tensor evaluated in this frame: all measurements of tensor or scalar fields can be thought of as relational observables. The lack of observables is a major critique of the current Asymptotic Safety program. However, in the last years, within the functional renormalisation group framework an equation to evaluate the flow and the scaling dimension of composite operators has been developed. Relational observables are therefore natural candidates for composite operators. We introduce an approach to compute the renormalisation group flow of relational observables in quantum gravity which evolve from their microscopic expressions towards the full quantum expectation value. These methods can be applied to a large class of relational observables within a derivative expansion for different physical coordinate systems. Based on arXiv:2112.02118.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dalius Stulga: Provable properties of asymptotic safety in the f(R) approximation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/Dalius-Stulga.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dalius Stulga: Provable properties of asymptotic safety in the f(R) approximation" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/Dalius-Stulga</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/07/Dalius-Stulga.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk I will describe how we can derive general properties of the fixed-point solutions to the flow equations in the f(R) approximation using a family of non-adaptive cutoffs. The full f(R) approximation results in complicated differential equations and makes analysis very difficult. However, progress can be made using analytic approaches. Firstly, solving the flow equations asymptotically at large curvature allows us to conclude that there are discrete set of fixed-point solutions. We can then use Sturm-Liouville techniques to draw conclusions about the properties of these fixed points and their eigenoperator spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk I will describe how we can derive general properties of the fixed-point solutions to the flow equations in the f(R) approximation using a family of non-adaptive cutoffs. The full f(R) approximation results in complicated differential equations and makes analysis very difficult. However, progress can be made using analytic approaches. Firstly, solving the flow equations asymptotically at large curvature allows us to conclude that there are discrete set of fixed-point solutions. We can then use Sturm-Liouville techniques to draw conclusions about the properties of these fixed points and their eigenoperator spectrum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tom Steudtner: Explaining B-Anomalies with safe Z’ extensions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/28/Tom-Steudtner.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tom Steudtner: Explaining B-Anomalies with safe Z’ extensions" /><published>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/28/Tom-Steudtner</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/28/Tom-Steudtner.html">&lt;p&gt;U(1)’ extensions of the SM with generation-dependent couplings to quarks and leptons are a popular explanation of anomalies in rare B-decays, such as the R_K and R_K* observables. However, a critical issue with such models is often ignored – most configurations feature a Landau pole in the new gauge coupling that is well below the Planck scale. In this talk, I will present an ansatz that avoids such Landau poles, stabilises the Higgs potential and remains well-behaved and predictive up to the Planck scale.  To these ends, we introduce three generations of vector-like standard model singlet fermions, an enlarged, flavourful scalar sector, and, possibly, right-handed neutrinos, all suitably charged under the U(1)′ gauge interaction. We identify several benchmark models consistent with theory as well as phenomenological constraints and their respective predictions of Wilson coefficients for a global b→s fit. We further investigate the complete two-loop running of gauge, Yukawa and quartic couplings up to the Planck scale to constrain low-energy parameters and map out the BSM critical surface. Moreover, some key phenomenological aspects are highlighted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">U(1)’ extensions of the SM with generation-dependent couplings to quarks and leptons are a popular explanation of anomalies in rare B-decays, such as the R_K and R_K* observables. However, a critical issue with such models is often ignored – most configurations feature a Landau pole in the new gauge coupling that is well below the Planck scale. In this talk, I will present an ansatz that avoids such Landau poles, stabilises the Higgs potential and remains well-behaved and predictive up to the Planck scale. To these ends, we introduce three generations of vector-like standard model singlet fermions, an enlarged, flavourful scalar sector, and, possibly, right-handed neutrinos, all suitably charged under the U(1)′ gauge interaction. We identify several benchmark models consistent with theory as well as phenomenological constraints and their respective predictions of Wilson coefficients for a global b→s fit. We further investigate the complete two-loop running of gauge, Yukawa and quartic couplings up to the Planck scale to constrain low-energy parameters and map out the BSM critical surface. Moreover, some key phenomenological aspects are highlighted.</summary></entry></feed>