<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-16T19:38:46+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Asymptotic Safety Seminars</title><subtitle>Asymptotic Safety Seminars. An international online seminar series. Since 2011.&gt;-</subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum" /><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html">&lt;p&gt;We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations.  By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations. By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes" /><published>2021-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html">&lt;p&gt;Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth%20Asante</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html">&lt;p&gt;A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models.  I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models. I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alicia Castro: FRG Approach to the Continuum Limit of Matrix Models of Quantum Gravity with Preferred Foliation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/30/Alicia-Castro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alicia Castro: FRG Approach to the Continuum Limit of Matrix Models of Quantum Gravity with Preferred Foliation" /><published>2020-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/30/Alicia-Castro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/30/Alicia-Castro.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk I will present the analysis of a dually-weighted Matrix Model which implements a preferred foliation in its dual-graph. By using the FRGE, we study the existence of fixed points and its universality class (CDT or Euclidean Matrix Models). We find first evidence that the FGRE is a useful exploratory tool for the investigation of continuum limits of dually-weighted tensor models and thus for the analytic investigation of the existence of the phases found numerically in the CDT and EDT approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk I will present the analysis of a dually-weighted Matrix Model which implements a preferred foliation in its dual-graph. By using the FRGE, we study the existence of fixed points and its universality class (CDT or Euclidean Matrix Models). We find first evidence that the FGRE is a useful exploratory tool for the investigation of continuum limits of dually-weighted tensor models and thus for the analytic investigation of the existence of the phases found numerically in the CDT and EDT approaches.</summary></entry></feed>