<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-10T10:46:46+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Asymptotic Safety Seminars</title><subtitle>Asymptotic Safety Seminars. An international online seminar series. Since 2011.&gt;-</subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Alex Mitchell-Lister: The continuum limit of quantum gravity at second order in perturbation theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/06/07/Alex-Mitchell-Lister.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alex Mitchell-Lister: The continuum limit of quantum gravity at second order in perturbation theory" /><published>2021-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/future/2021/06/07/Alex-Mitchell-Lister</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/06/07/Alex-Mitchell-Lister.html">&lt;p&gt;preliminary abstract:
We show that perturbative quantum gravity based on the Einstein–Hilbert action, has a novel continuum limit. The renormalized trajectory emanates from the Gaussian fixed point along (marginally) relevant directions but enters the diffeomorphism invariant subspace only well below a dynamically generated scale. We show that for pure quantum gravity to second order in perturbation theory, and with vanishing cosmological constant, the result is the same as computed in the standard quantisation. Although this case is renormalizable at second order for kinematic reasons, the structure we uncover works in general. One possibility is that gravity has a genuine consistent continuum limit even though it has an infinite number couplings. However we also suggest a possible non-perturbative mechanism, based on the parabolic properties of these flow equations, which would fix all higher order couplings in terms of Newton’s constant and the cosmological constant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><category term="future" /><summary type="html">preliminary abstract: We show that perturbative quantum gravity based on the Einstein–Hilbert action, has a novel continuum limit. The renormalized trajectory emanates from the Gaussian fixed point along (marginally) relevant directions but enters the diffeomorphism invariant subspace only well below a dynamically generated scale. We show that for pure quantum gravity to second order in perturbation theory, and with vanishing cosmological constant, the result is the same as computed in the standard quantisation. Although this case is renormalizable at second order for kinematic reasons, the structure we uncover works in general. One possibility is that gravity has a genuine consistent continuum limit even though it has an infinite number couplings. However we also suggest a possible non-perturbative mechanism, based on the parabolic properties of these flow equations, which would fix all higher order couplings in terms of Newton’s constant and the cosmological constant.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adrien Florio: Searching for continuous phase transitions in 5D SU(2) lattice gauge theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/31/Adrien-Florio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adrien Florio: Searching for continuous phase transitions in 5D SU(2) lattice gauge theory" /><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/31/Adrien-Florio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/31/Adrien-Florio.html">&lt;p&gt;preliminary abstract:
We study the phase diagram of 5-dimensional SU(2)SU(2)SU(2) Yang-Mills theory on the lattice. We consider two extensions of the fundamental plaquette Wilson action in the search for the continuous phase transition suggested by the 4+ϵ4+\epsilon4+ϵ expansion. The extensions correspond to new terms in the action: i) a unit size plaquette in the adjoint representation or ii) a two-unit sided square plaquette in the fundamental representation. We use Monte Carlo to sample the first and second derivative of the entropy near the confinement phase transition, with lattices up to 12512^{5}125. While we exclude the presence of a second order phase transition in the parameter space we sampled for model i), our data is not conclusive in some regions of the parameter space of model ii).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><category term="future" /><summary type="html">preliminary abstract: We study the phase diagram of 5-dimensional SU(2)SU(2)SU(2) Yang-Mills theory on the lattice. We consider two extensions of the fundamental plaquette Wilson action in the search for the continuous phase transition suggested by the 4+ϵ4+\epsilon4+ϵ expansion. The extensions correspond to new terms in the action: i) a unit size plaquette in the adjoint representation or ii) a two-unit sided square plaquette in the fundamental representation. We use Monte Carlo to sample the first and second derivative of the entropy near the confinement phase transition, with lattices up to 12512^{5}125. While we exclude the presence of a second order phase transition in the parameter space we sampled for model i), our data is not conclusive in some regions of the parameter space of model ii).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abdol Sabor Salek: A curvature bound from gravitational catalysis in thermal backgrounds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/17/Abdol-Sabor-Salek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abdol Sabor Salek: A curvature bound from gravitational catalysis in thermal backgrounds" /><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/17/Abdol-Sabor-Salek</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/future/2021/05/17/Abdol-Sabor-Salek.html">&lt;p&gt;preliminary abstract:
We investigate the phenomenon of gravitational catalysis, i.e., curvature-induced chiral symmetry breaking and fermion mass generation, at finite temperature. Using a scale-dependent analysis, we derive a thermal bound on the curvature of local patches of spacetime. This bound quantifies regions in parameter space that remain unaffected by gravitational catalysis and thus are compatible with the existence of light fermions as observed in Nature. While finite temperature generically relaxes the curvature bound, we observe a comparatively strong dependence of the phenomenon on the details of the curvature. Our bound can be applied to scenarios of quantum gravity, as any realistic candidate has to accommodate a sufficient number of light fermions. We argue that our bound therefore represents a test for quantum gravity scenarios: a suitably averaged spacetime in the (trans-)Planckian regime that satisfies our curvature bound does not induce correspondingly large Planckian fermion masses by gravitational catalysis. The temperature dependence derived in this work facilitates to follow the fate of gravitational catalysis during the thermal history of the (quantum) universe. In an application to the Asymptotic Safety scenario of quantum gravity, our bound translates into a temperature-dependent upper bound on the number of fermion flavors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><category term="future" /><summary type="html">preliminary abstract: We investigate the phenomenon of gravitational catalysis, i.e., curvature-induced chiral symmetry breaking and fermion mass generation, at finite temperature. Using a scale-dependent analysis, we derive a thermal bound on the curvature of local patches of spacetime. This bound quantifies regions in parameter space that remain unaffected by gravitational catalysis and thus are compatible with the existence of light fermions as observed in Nature. While finite temperature generically relaxes the curvature bound, we observe a comparatively strong dependence of the phenomenon on the details of the curvature. Our bound can be applied to scenarios of quantum gravity, as any realistic candidate has to accommodate a sufficient number of light fermions. We argue that our bound therefore represents a test for quantum gravity scenarios: a suitably averaged spacetime in the (trans-)Planckian regime that satisfies our curvature bound does not induce correspondingly large Planckian fermion masses by gravitational catalysis. The temperature dependence derived in this work facilitates to follow the fate of gravitational catalysis during the thermal history of the (quantum) universe. In an application to the Asymptotic Safety scenario of quantum gravity, our bound translates into a temperature-dependent upper bound on the number of fermion flavors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum" /><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html">&lt;p&gt;We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations.  By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations. By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes" /><published>2021-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html">&lt;p&gt;Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth%20Asante</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html">&lt;p&gt;A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models.  I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models. I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Passant Ali: Constraints on discrete global symmetries in quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passant Ali: Constraints on discrete global symmetries in quantum gravity" /><published>2021-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali.html">&lt;p&gt;The question whether global symmetries can be realized in quantum-gravity-matter-systems has far-reaching phenomenological consequences. During my talk I will discuss evidence we found that within an asymptotically safe context, discrete global symmetries of the form Z_n,n &amp;gt;4, cannot be realized in a near-perturbative regime. In contrast, an effective-field-theory approach to quantum gravity might feature such symmetries, providing a mechanism to generate mass hierarchies in the infrared, without the need for additional fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">The question whether global symmetries can be realized in quantum-gravity-matter-systems has far-reaching phenomenological consequences. During my talk I will discuss evidence we found that within an asymptotically safe context, discrete global symmetries of the form Z_n,n &amp;gt;4, cannot be realized in a near-perturbative regime. In contrast, an effective-field-theory approach to quantum gravity might feature such symmetries, providing a mechanism to generate mass hierarchies in the infrared, without the need for additional fine-tuning.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renata Ferrero: Dynamical diffeomorphisms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renata Ferrero: Dynamical diffeomorphisms" /><published>2021-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero.html">&lt;p&gt;We consider a class of models for dynamical dark energy: we construct a general effective dynamics for diffeomorphisms of spacetime, in a fixed external metric. Though related to familiar models of scalar fields as coordinates, our models have subtly different properties, both at kinematical and dynamical level. The energy-momentum tensor consists of two independently conserved parts. The background solution is the identity diffeomorphism and the energy-momentum tensor of this solution gives rise to an effective cosmological constant. We will also discuss possible applications to the construction of relational observables. Based on arXiv:2012.04507.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We consider a class of models for dynamical dark energy: we construct a general effective dynamics for diffeomorphisms of spacetime, in a fixed external metric. Though related to familiar models of scalar fields as coordinates, our models have subtly different properties, both at kinematical and dynamical level. The energy-momentum tensor consists of two independently conserved parts. The background solution is the identity diffeomorphism and the energy-momentum tensor of this solution gives rise to an effective cosmological constant. We will also discuss possible applications to the construction of relational observables. Based on arXiv:2012.04507.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yannick Kluth: Fixed Points of Quantum Gravity and the Dimensionality of the UV Critical Surface</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yannick Kluth: Fixed Points of Quantum Gravity and the Dimensionality of the UV Critical Surface" /><published>2020-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk, the fixed point structure of asymptotically safe quantum gravity is tested for actions containing squares of the Riemann tensor and the Ricci scalar curvature. After explaining the basic setup, I show results of a numerical scan leading to three stable fixed points which have been analysed including up to 144 different curvature invariants. Properties such as UV critical surfaces, convergence and equations of motion are discussed and compared to literature results in asymptotically safe quantum gravity. Moreover, it is shown how eigenvectors can be used as a tool to understand the composition of eigenvalues in terms of curvature monomials by use of a new equal weight condition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk, the fixed point structure of asymptotically safe quantum gravity is tested for actions containing squares of the Riemann tensor and the Ricci scalar curvature. After explaining the basic setup, I show results of a numerical scan leading to three stable fixed points which have been analysed including up to 144 different curvature invariants. Properties such as UV critical surfaces, convergence and equations of motion are discussed and compared to literature results in asymptotically safe quantum gravity. Moreover, it is shown how eigenvectors can be used as a tool to understand the composition of eigenvalues in terms of curvature monomials by use of a new equal weight condition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alessia Platania: Non-perturbative unitarity and fictitious ghosts in quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alessia Platania: Non-perturbative unitarity and fictitious ghosts in quantum gravity" /><published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania.html">&lt;p&gt;According to the asymptotic-safety conjecture, a (non-perturbatively) renormalizable quantum field theory of gravity could be constructed based on the existence of a non-trivial fixed point of the gravitational renormalization group flow. The existence of this fixed point can be established, e.g., via the non-perturbative methods of the functional renormalization group (FRG). In practice, the use of the FRG methods requires to work within truncations of the gravitational action, and higher-derivative operators naturally lead to the presence of several poles in the propagator. The question is whether these poles represent a real problem for the unitarity of the theory. In this talk I will show with explicit examples that the inclusion of quantum effects at all scales is of crucial importance to assess unitarity of field theories. In particular, poles appearing in truncations of the action could correspond to fake degrees of freedom of the theory. Possible conditions to determine, within truncations, whether a pole represents a fake or a genuine degree of freedom of the theory will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">According to the asymptotic-safety conjecture, a (non-perturbatively) renormalizable quantum field theory of gravity could be constructed based on the existence of a non-trivial fixed point of the gravitational renormalization group flow. The existence of this fixed point can be established, e.g., via the non-perturbative methods of the functional renormalization group (FRG). In practice, the use of the FRG methods requires to work within truncations of the gravitational action, and higher-derivative operators naturally lead to the presence of several poles in the propagator. The question is whether these poles represent a real problem for the unitarity of the theory. In this talk I will show with explicit examples that the inclusion of quantum effects at all scales is of crucial importance to assess unitarity of field theories. In particular, poles appearing in truncations of the action could correspond to fake degrees of freedom of the theory. Possible conditions to determine, within truncations, whether a pole represents a fake or a genuine degree of freedom of the theory will be discussed.</summary></entry></feed>