<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4001/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-03T01:30:47+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Asymptotic Safety Seminars</title><subtitle>Asymptotic Safety Seminars. An international online seminar series. Since 2011.&gt;-</subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Judah Unmuth-Yockey: Newtonian binding from lattice quantum" /><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2021/04/12/post-Judah-Unmuth-Yockey.html">&lt;p&gt;We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations.  By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We consider a free scalar field on Euclidean dynamical triangulations. By studying the 1-particle and 2-particle correlation functions, we extract the binding energy between two scalar particles. We extrapolate our data for the binding energy to the continuum, infinite volume limit, and find a result consistent with the expected power-law behavior of the binding energy in four-dimensional space-time. We also report on an estimate for Newton’s gravitational coupling, G.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raúl Carballo Rubio: Mass inflation and the semiclassical limit of quantum black holes" /><published>2021-03-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2021/03/29/Raul-Carballo-Rubio.html">&lt;p&gt;Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">Geometries describing static non-singular black holes have been obtained in suitable limits of various quantum gravity frameworks, including asymptotic safety. After a brief review of the underlying geometric reasons behind this universality, and a discussion of the similarities between these geometries and classical charged/rotating black holes, the talk will focus on the description of mass inflation in this extended setting. The presentation will be pedagogical, with emphasis on the assumptions, implications, and limitations of existing studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seth Kurankyi Asante: Effective spin foam models for four dimensional quantum gravity" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2021/02/22/Seth%20Asante</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2021/02/22/Seth-Asante.html">&lt;p&gt;A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models.  I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">A number of approaches to four-dimensional quantum gravity, such as loop quantum gravity and holography, situate areas as their fundamental variables. These area variables are however, not free but satisfy certain constraints which allow for a consistent gluing. I will introduce a family of ‘effective’ spin foam models that incorporate a quantum area spectrum and impose gluing constraints as strongly as possible. The simplicity of these models allows to clarify some issues appearing in semi classical analysis of generic spin foam models. I will describe initial attempts toward testing quantum gravity equations on non-trivial spacetime boundaries. Numerical computations reveal a very rich structure of the amplitudes and a good semiclassical behaviour in a restricted regime of the parameter space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Passant Ali: Constraints on discrete global symmetries in quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passant Ali: Constraints on discrete global symmetries in quantum gravity" /><published>2021-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2021/02/12/Passant-Ali.html">&lt;p&gt;The question whether global symmetries can be realized in quantum-gravity-matter-systems has far-reaching phenomenological consequences. During my talk I will discuss evidence we found that within an asymptotically safe context, discrete global symmetries of the form Z_n,n &amp;gt;4, cannot be realized in a near-perturbative regime. In contrast, an effective-field-theory approach to quantum gravity might feature such symmetries, providing a mechanism to generate mass hierarchies in the infrared, without the need for additional fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">The question whether global symmetries can be realized in quantum-gravity-matter-systems has far-reaching phenomenological consequences. During my talk I will discuss evidence we found that within an asymptotically safe context, discrete global symmetries of the form Z_n,n &amp;gt;4, cannot be realized in a near-perturbative regime. In contrast, an effective-field-theory approach to quantum gravity might feature such symmetries, providing a mechanism to generate mass hierarchies in the infrared, without the need for additional fine-tuning.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renata Ferrero: Dynamical diffeomorphisms</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renata Ferrero: Dynamical diffeomorphisms" /><published>2021-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2021/01/25/Renata-Ferrero.html">&lt;p&gt;We consider a class of models for dynamical dark energy: we construct a general effective dynamics for diffeomorphisms of spacetime, in a fixed external metric. Though related to familiar models of scalar fields as coordinates, our models have subtly different properties, both at kinematical and dynamical level. The energy-momentum tensor consists of two independently conserved parts. The background solution is the identity diffeomorphism and the energy-momentum tensor of this solution gives rise to an effective cosmological constant. We will also discuss possible applications to the construction of relational observables. Based on arXiv:2012.04507.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">We consider a class of models for dynamical dark energy: we construct a general effective dynamics for diffeomorphisms of spacetime, in a fixed external metric. Though related to familiar models of scalar fields as coordinates, our models have subtly different properties, both at kinematical and dynamical level. The energy-momentum tensor consists of two independently conserved parts. The background solution is the identity diffeomorphism and the energy-momentum tensor of this solution gives rise to an effective cosmological constant. We will also discuss possible applications to the construction of relational observables. Based on arXiv:2012.04507.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yannick Kluth: Fixed Points of Quantum Gravity and the Dimensionality of the UV Critical Surface</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yannick Kluth: Fixed Points of Quantum Gravity and the Dimensionality of the UV Critical Surface" /><published>2020-11-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/23/Yannick-Kluth.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk, the fixed point structure of asymptotically safe quantum gravity is tested for actions containing squares of the Riemann tensor and the Ricci scalar curvature. After explaining the basic setup, I show results of a numerical scan leading to three stable fixed points which have been analysed including up to 144 different curvature invariants. Properties such as UV critical surfaces, convergence and equations of motion are discussed and compared to literature results in asymptotically safe quantum gravity. Moreover, it is shown how eigenvectors can be used as a tool to understand the composition of eigenvalues in terms of curvature monomials by use of a new equal weight condition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk, the fixed point structure of asymptotically safe quantum gravity is tested for actions containing squares of the Riemann tensor and the Ricci scalar curvature. After explaining the basic setup, I show results of a numerical scan leading to three stable fixed points which have been analysed including up to 144 different curvature invariants. Properties such as UV critical surfaces, convergence and equations of motion are discussed and compared to literature results in asymptotically safe quantum gravity. Moreover, it is shown how eigenvectors can be used as a tool to understand the composition of eigenvalues in terms of curvature monomials by use of a new equal weight condition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alessia Platania: Non-perturbative unitarity and fictitious ghosts in quantum gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alessia Platania: Non-perturbative unitarity and fictitious ghosts in quantum gravity" /><published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/16/Alessia-Platania.html">&lt;p&gt;According to the asymptotic-safety conjecture, a (non-perturbatively) renormalizable quantum field theory of gravity could be constructed based on the existence of a non-trivial fixed point of the gravitational renormalization group flow. The existence of this fixed point can be established, e.g., via the non-perturbative methods of the functional renormalization group (FRG). In practice, the use of the FRG methods requires to work within truncations of the gravitational action, and higher-derivative operators naturally lead to the presence of several poles in the propagator. The question is whether these poles represent a real problem for the unitarity of the theory. In this talk I will show with explicit examples that the inclusion of quantum effects at all scales is of crucial importance to assess unitarity of field theories. In particular, poles appearing in truncations of the action could correspond to fake degrees of freedom of the theory. Possible conditions to determine, within truncations, whether a pole represents a fake or a genuine degree of freedom of the theory will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">According to the asymptotic-safety conjecture, a (non-perturbatively) renormalizable quantum field theory of gravity could be constructed based on the existence of a non-trivial fixed point of the gravitational renormalization group flow. The existence of this fixed point can be established, e.g., via the non-perturbative methods of the functional renormalization group (FRG). In practice, the use of the FRG methods requires to work within truncations of the gravitational action, and higher-derivative operators naturally lead to the presence of several poles in the propagator. The question is whether these poles represent a real problem for the unitarity of the theory. In this talk I will show with explicit examples that the inclusion of quantum effects at all scales is of crucial importance to assess unitarity of field theories. In particular, poles appearing in truncations of the action could correspond to fake degrees of freedom of the theory. Possible conditions to determine, within truncations, whether a pole represents a fake or a genuine degree of freedom of the theory will be discussed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Enrico Sessolo: Flavor anomalies from asymptotically safe gravity</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/09/Enrico-Sessolo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enrico Sessolo: Flavor anomalies from asymptotically safe gravity" /><published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2020/11/09/Enrico-Sessolo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2020/11/09/Enrico-Sessolo.html">&lt;p&gt;I will describe how the framework of asymptotically safe quantum gravity can be employed to derive novel predictions for some well-known new physics solutions to the LHCb flavor anomalies. After a brief review of the experimental evidence for new physics signatures in flavor processes, I will single out scalar leptoquarks as a very simple explanation and show that their gauge and Yukawa couplings may feature an interactive UV fixed point. Following RGE evolution one can thus predict the low-energy values of the leptoquark Yukawa matrix elements and significantly narrow down the allowed leptoquark mass range. To be in agreement with the b –&amp;gt; s anomalies, the leptoquark mass should lie
between 4 and 10 TeV, which puts it entirely in reach of a hadron-hadron collider with 100 TeV c.o.m. energy. I will finally touch on gravity-driven solutions to the b –&amp;gt; c anomalies and highlight the caveats and limitations that apply to this procedure for deriving predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">I will describe how the framework of asymptotically safe quantum gravity can be employed to derive novel predictions for some well-known new physics solutions to the LHCb flavor anomalies. After a brief review of the experimental evidence for new physics signatures in flavor processes, I will single out scalar leptoquarks as a very simple explanation and show that their gauge and Yukawa couplings may feature an interactive UV fixed point. Following RGE evolution one can thus predict the low-energy values of the leptoquark Yukawa matrix elements and significantly narrow down the allowed leptoquark mass range. To be in agreement with the b –&amp;gt; s anomalies, the leptoquark mass should lie between 4 and 10 TeV, which puts it entirely in reach of a hadron-hadron collider with 100 TeV c.o.m. energy. I will finally touch on gravity-driven solutions to the b –&amp;gt; c anomalies and highlight the caveats and limitations that apply to this procedure for deriving predictions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jesse Daas: Asymptotically Safe Gravity with Fermions</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2020/09/14/Jesse-Daas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jesse Daas: Asymptotically Safe Gravity with Fermions" /><published>2020-09-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2020/09/14/Jesse-Daas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2020/09/14/Jesse-Daas.html">&lt;p&gt;In this talk the fixed point structure of gravity-fermion systems on a curved background spacetime will be discussed using the functional renormalization group equation. The effective average action is approximated by the Einstein-Hilbert action supplemented by a fermion kinetic term and a coupling of the fermion-bilinears to the spacetime curvature. The latter interaction is singled out based on a “smart truncation building principle”. The resulting renormalization group flow possesses two families of interacting renormalization group fixed points extending to any number of fermions. The first family exhibits an upper bound on the number of fermions for which the fixed points could provide a phenomenologically interesting high-energy completion via the asymptotic safety mechanism. The second family comes without such a bound. The inclusion of the non-minimal gravity-matter interaction is crucial for discriminating the two families. some insights into the origin of the strong regulator-dependence of the fixed point structure reported in earlier literature is also provided. The relation of our findings to studies of the same system based on a vertex expansion of the effective average action around a flat background spacetime will also be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">In this talk the fixed point structure of gravity-fermion systems on a curved background spacetime will be discussed using the functional renormalization group equation. The effective average action is approximated by the Einstein-Hilbert action supplemented by a fermion kinetic term and a coupling of the fermion-bilinears to the spacetime curvature. The latter interaction is singled out based on a “smart truncation building principle”. The resulting renormalization group flow possesses two families of interacting renormalization group fixed points extending to any number of fermions. The first family exhibits an upper bound on the number of fermions for which the fixed points could provide a phenomenologically interesting high-energy completion via the asymptotic safety mechanism. The second family comes without such a bound. The inclusion of the non-minimal gravity-matter interaction is crucial for discriminating the two families. some insights into the origin of the strong regulator-dependence of the fixed point structure reported in earlier literature is also provided. The relation of our findings to studies of the same system based on a vertex expansion of the effective average action around a flat background spacetime will also be discussed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jobst Ziebell: Asymptotically Safe QED</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2020/07/20/Jobst-Ziebell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jobst Ziebell: Asymptotically Safe QED" /><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2020/07/20/Jobst-Ziebell</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2020/07/20/Jobst-Ziebell.html">&lt;p&gt;High-energy completeness of quantum electrodynamics (QED) can be induced by an interacting ultraviolet fixed point of the renormalization flow. We provide evidence for the existence of two of such fixed points in the subspace spanned by the gauge coupling, the electron mass and the Pauli spin-field coupling. Renormalization group trajectories emanating from these fixed points correspond to asymptotically safe theories that are free from the Landau pole problem. We analyze the resulting universality classes defined by the fixed points, determine the corresponding critical exponents, study the resulting phase diagram, and quantify the stability of our results with respect to a systematic expansion scheme. We also compute high-energy complete flows towards the long-range physics. We observe the existence of a renormalization group trajectory that interconnects one of the interacting fixed points with the physical low-energy behavior of QED as measured in experiment. Within pure QED, we estimate the crossover from perturbative QED to the asymptotically safe fixed point regime to occur somewhat above the Planck scale but far below the scale of the Landau pole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html">High-energy completeness of quantum electrodynamics (QED) can be induced by an interacting ultraviolet fixed point of the renormalization flow. We provide evidence for the existence of two of such fixed points in the subspace spanned by the gauge coupling, the electron mass and the Pauli spin-field coupling. Renormalization group trajectories emanating from these fixed points correspond to asymptotically safe theories that are free from the Landau pole problem. We analyze the resulting universality classes defined by the fixed points, determine the corresponding critical exponents, study the resulting phase diagram, and quantify the stability of our results with respect to a systematic expansion scheme. We also compute high-energy complete flows towards the long-range physics. We observe the existence of a renormalization group trajectory that interconnects one of the interacting fixed points with the physical low-energy behavior of QED as measured in experiment. Within pure QED, we estimate the crossover from perturbative QED to the asymptotically safe fixed point regime to occur somewhat above the Planck scale but far below the scale of the Landau pole.</summary></entry></feed>